Sidney Lanier Collection
Sidney Lanier Collection
1859-1949
0.5 linear ft.
Contains published material and a small amount of miscellany about the American poet and musician. Some letters by Lanier himself.
3471960
Biographical History
Sidney Lanier (1842-1881) was an American poet and musician. He was a soldier in the Confederate army, a lawyer and a teacher before beginning to write poetry, and eventually joined the faculty at Johns Hopkins University where he lectured on the English novelists and Elizabethan and Anglo-Saxon poets. He took up the flute in the late 1870s or early 1880s, and for a time played with the Peabody Orchestra in Baltimore, Maryland. He was known for combining music and poetry in a proselike form known as logaoedic verse.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Sidney Lanier Collection consists of correspondence, published material, and a small amount of miscellany. Included are several copies of a musical piece entitled "The Grasshopper: A Tragic Cantata." The connection of this piece to Lanier is unknown, as he is not listed as either the composer or the lyricist. The collection was likely accumulated by John S. Mayfield.
Correspondence contains outgoing letters from Lanier.
Published material consists of items about Lanier (nothing by him).
Miscellaneous consists of items about the American poet and musician, including correspondence between John S. Mayfield and others.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is in chronological order. Published material is alphabetical by type of material. Miscellaneous correspondence is arranged chronologically and the printing plates are in no particular order.
Related Material
has a number of published works by and about Sidney Lanier in both our regular and Rare Books holdings. Please search for these related materials.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Music; Emmett, Chris, 1886-1971 -- The general and the poet.; Lanier, Sidney, 1842-1881.; Mayfield, John S., 1904-1983 -- Sidney Lanier's immoral bird.; Mayfield, John S., 1904-1983 -- Sidney Lanier in Texas.; Mayfield, John S., 1904-1983 -- Some new facts concerning Sidney Lanier in Florida.; Beeson, Leola Selman -- Sidney Lanier at Oglethorpe University.; Johnston, Albert Sidney, 1803-1862.; Randolph, Innes, 1837-1887 -- The grasshopper: a tragic cantata.; American poetry -- 19th century.; American poetry -- Southern States.; Georgia -- Intellectual life -- 19th century.; Books.; Correspondence.; Printing plates.; Sheet music.; Biographers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - from Lanier, 1859-1880 (Box 1)
- Published material
  - The general and the poet, Chris Emmett, 1940; comparative biographical sketches of Sidney Lanier and General Albert Sidney Johnston; signed and inscribed to John S. Mayfield (Box 1)
  - The grasshopper: a tragic cantata, Innes Randolph, 1878; multiple copies, various sizes and colors (Box 1)
  - Sidney Lanier's immoral bird, John S. Mayfield, May-June 1935; reprint from The American Book Collector; 3 copies (Box 1)
  - Sidney Lanier at Oglethorpe University, Leola Selman Beeson, 1936; signed and inscribed to John S. Mayfield (Box 1)
  - Sidney Lanier in Texas, John S. Mayfield, 1932; 2 copies (Box 1)
  - Some new facts concerning Sidney Lanier in Florida, John S. Mayfield, Nov 1935; reprint from The Johns Hopkins Alumni Magazine (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Correspondence, 1935-1949; undated; Mayfield and publishers, some of the correspondence refers to letters from Lanier found in this collection (Box 1)
  - Printing plates, small copper plates, backed with wood blocks; portrait of Lanier with dates; 5 items (Box 1)